<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->
<!DOCTYPE rss PUBLIC "-//Netscape Communications//DTD RSS 0.91//EN" "http://my.netscape.com/publish/formats/rss-0.91.dtd">

<rss version="0.91">
  <channel>
    <title>Ocean of Awareness   </title>
    <link>http://jeffreykegler.github.com/Ocean-of-Awareness-blog</link>
    <description>Ocean of Awareness.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Perl and Parsing 8: The Where and Why of Rejection</title>
    <link>http://jeffreykegler.github.com/Ocean-of-Awareness-blog/2011/03/24#perl-and-parsing-8-the-where-and-why-of-rejection</link>
    <description>&lt;h1&gt;Why Perl is Just Not That Into Your Syntax&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.perl.org/users/jeffrey_kegler/2011/01/perl-and-parsing-6-error-handling.html&quot;&gt;
In a previous post&lt;/a&gt;,
I noted that Perl often cannot precisely
locate syntax errors in its scripts.
Still less can it identify the exact problem.
In this post, I will demonstrate an experimental
utility which does
pinpoint Perl syntax errors,
&lt;a href=&quot;#NOTE1&quot;&gt;precisely indicating where and what the problem is&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;Here's my example
&lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.perl.org/users/jeffrey_kegler/2011/01/perl-and-parsing-6-error-handling.html&quot;&gt;
from the previous post&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;pre&gt;
&lt;code class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
my $lyric =
'Sloopy wears a red dress, yeah
As old as the hills
but when sloopy wears that red dress, yeah
you know it gives me the chills
Sloopy when I see you walking, 
walking down the street
I say don\'t worry sloopy, girl
You belong to me'~!@$%^&amp;*()_+;
print &quot;$lyric\n&quot;;

&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here is Perl's output for the error:
&lt;pre&gt;
&lt;code class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
Bareword found where operator expected at bomb2.pl line 9, near &quot;)_&quot;
        (Missing operator before _?)
syntax error at bomb2.pl line 9, near &quot;You belong to me'~&quot;
  (Might be a runaway multi-line '' string starting on line 2)
Execution of bomb2.pl aborted due to compilation errors.
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
As I said
&lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.perl.org/users/jeffrey_kegler/2011/01/perl-and-parsing-6-error-handling.html&quot;&gt;
in that previous post&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;var&gt;perl&lt;/var&gt;
clearly has very
little idea where things went wrong -- it's guessing.
&lt;h1&gt;Pinpointing the Error&lt;/h1&gt;

At this point, let me give away the ending.
The point of failure is the very first special symbol: the tilde.
When I ran my fingers from left to right across the top of my keyboard,
I was hoping to produce a more complicated example.
But perhaps it is just as well I did not.
&lt;p&gt;
Here,
&lt;a href=&quot;#NOTE2&quot;&gt;
from my experimental Marpa-based utility&lt;/a&gt;,
is what
Perl is looking for when it encounters the tilde:
The dot in the rules indicates how far the parse has already progressed.
&lt;pre&gt;
line -&gt; label sideff . SEMI
sideff -&gt; expr . IF expr
sideff -&gt; expr . UNLESS expr
sideff -&gt; expr . WHILE expr
sideff -&gt; expr . UNTIL iexpr
sideff -&gt; expr . FOR expr
sideff -&gt; expr . WHEN expr
or_expr -&gt; or_expr . OROP and_expr
or_expr -&gt; or_expr . DOROP and_expr
and_expr -&gt; and_expr . ANDOP argexpr
argexpr -&gt; argexpr . COMMA
argexpr -&gt; argexpr . COMMA term
term_listop -&gt; term_cond . ASSIGNOP term_listop
term_assign -&gt; term_cond . ASSIGNOP term_assign
term_cond -&gt; term_dotdot . QUESTION term_cond COLON term_cond
term_dotdot -&gt; term_oror . DOTDOT term_oror
term_oror -&gt; term_oror . OROR term_andand
term_oror -&gt; term_oror . DORDOR term_andand
term_andand -&gt; term_andand . ANDAND term_bitorop
term_bitorop -&gt; term_bitorop . BITOROP term_bitandop
term_bitandop -&gt; term_bitandop . BITANDOP term_eqop
term_eqop -&gt; term_relop . EQOP term_relop
term_relop -&gt; term_uniop . RELOP term_uniop
term_shiftop -&gt; term_shiftop . SHIFTOP term_addop
term_addop -&gt; term_addop . ADDOP term_mulop
term_mulop -&gt; term_mulop . MULOP term_matchop
term_matchop -&gt; term_matchop . MATCHOP term_uminus
term_powop -&gt; term_increment . POWOP term_powop
term_increment -&gt; term_arrow . POSTINC
term_increment -&gt; term_arrow . POSTDEC
term_arrow -&gt; term_arrow . ARROW method LPAREN listexprcom RPAREN
term_arrow -&gt; term_arrow . ARROW method
subscripted -&gt; term_hi . ARROW LSQUARE expr RSQUARE
subscripted -&gt; term_hi . ARROW LCURLY expr SEMI RCURLY
subscripted -&gt; term_hi . ARROW LPAREN RPAREN
subscripted -&gt; term_hi . ARROW LPAREN expr RPAREN
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The names of the symbols are based on those in &lt;var&gt;perly.y&lt;/var&gt;.
Operators are not shown symbolically, but are indicated with the name
in caps: &quot;POSTINC&quot; instead of &quot;++&quot;.
&lt;a href=&quot;#NOTE2&quot;&gt;Terms are suffixed with their precedence&lt;/a&gt;:
&quot;term_assignop&quot; is the symbol
for terms with the same precedence as the assignment operator.
&quot;term_hi&quot; is the symbol for terms at the highest precedence level.
&lt;p&gt;
A tilde, when it is a single-character Perl operator,
is always a prefix unary operator.
Tildes also form part of several multi-character operators,
but that is not the case here.
Here is what Perl is looking for
when it encounters the tilde:
&lt;ul&gt;

&lt;li&gt;A semicolon that would end the statement.  (Statements
are called &lt;var&gt;line&lt;/var&gt;'s internally by &lt;var&gt;perly.y&lt;/var&gt;.)
&lt;li&gt;The postfix conditonal keywords.
&lt;li&gt;A lot of binary operators.
&lt;li&gt;A couple of postfix unary operators.
These, if found, will produce
a compile-time complaint about incrementing a constant.
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
No prefix unary operator is in the above list,
and the parse fails here.
&lt;h1&gt;About the Utility Used in This Post&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding the exact point of failure and the exact
reasons would seem like something that you'd want in a parser.
But in fact, production languages have tended to be like Perl --
they try to indicate the general area of a syntax problem
and to make a good guess as to its nature.
But they leave it to the programmer to figure out exactly where they failed
and why.
&lt;p&gt;Marpa, then, is unusual, in that for any grammar you can write in BNF,
and any input, it will either produce a parse, or a precise characterization
of the failure.
Marpa::XS::Perl
is still experimental and under development.
As I tackle tasks (like preparing this post, for example)
I add the necessary capabilities.
An example of what my utility cannot yet do is deal with
floating point constants.
(They're not hard, I just haven't encountered them yet in a test case.)
&lt;p&gt;My original intent with Marpa::XS::Perl was to use it for snippets,
and for academic and toy examples,
and it cannot yet deal with production Perl
code.
My purpose so far
has been to demonstrate that Marpa could be the basis
of a practical Perl parsing utility.
&lt;h1&gt;Notes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;NOTE1&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Note 1&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:
Of course, in one sense, the exact nature of the problem depends
on what the person writing the script intended, and on this
my utility has not a clue.
In this post, &quot;finding the exact problem&quot; means finding the exact
location of a parse failure, and finding exactly what &lt;var&gt;perl&lt;/var&gt;
was looking for when
&lt;var&gt;perl&lt;/var&gt; did not find what
&lt;var&gt;perl&lt;/var&gt; wanted to find.
&lt;p&gt;
In determining the &quot;exact location of parse failure&quot;,
I also avoid mind-reading.
I use a definition taken from the parsing literature:
In a rejected token stream,
the point of failure is the first token
which made a successful parse impossible.
In other words, if you encounter a token which cannot possibly
be part of a successful parse, given the input you've already
read, that token is the point of failure.
Looking at it from the opposite point of view,
if you can find some additonal
input that makes the parse succeed,
you have not yet found a point of failure.
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;NOTE2&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Note 2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:
To be precise, the output in this post was automatically generated
by my utility, then edited for readability.
Specifically, the edits removed
those lines which were for rules with the dot
at the end,
and removed rule numbers and token
numbers from the beginnings of the lines.
Since
rules with the dot at the end are completed, they do not
generate any expectations for future tokens,
and are irrelevant here.
Similarly, in this context
the internal rule numbers and location numbers would be clutter.
While I made these readability edits by hand, they were rote
and could easily have been automated.
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;NOTE3&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Note 3&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;:
Unlike in textbook BNF,
the BNF in &lt;var&gt;perly.y&lt;/var&gt; does not have a separate symbol for terms
of each precedence.  
The BNF in
&lt;var&gt;perly.y&lt;/var&gt; is wildly ambiguous,
unlike the Perl language.
&lt;var&gt;perly.y&lt;/var&gt; uses a tie-breaking technique,
in combination with the BNF,
to assign precedence.
While some use of this kind of tie-breaking is standard in &lt;var&gt;yacc&lt;/var&gt;,
for the Perl parser, Larry used it far more boldly than had been the practice before.
Or for that matter, has been since.
This is very important aspect of Perl parsing, one on which I've been planning to post.</description>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Progress on Marpa::XS</title>
    <link>http://jeffreykegler.github.com/Ocean-of-Awareness-blog/2011/03/17#progress-on-marpaxs</link>
    <description>&lt;h1&gt;A Faster Marpa&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been converting Marpa from Pure Perl to C.
For those who don't know,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://search.cpan.org/dist/Marpa/&quot;&gt;Marpa&lt;/a&gt;
is a parser generator
which parses any grammar you can write in BNF.
If the grammar is
&lt;a href=&quot;#NOTE1&quot;&gt;one of those which can be parsed
by yacc,
by recursive descent or as a regular expression&lt;/a&gt;,
Marpa parses it
&lt;a href=&quot;#NOTE2&quot;&gt;in linear time&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;Marpa's core algorithm does no system calls.
It is almost 100% pointer twiddling.
There is no floating point, and very little integer arithmetic.
It's as if it was made to order to show C in its very best light.
&lt;p&gt;I expected converting the Perl implementation
to C to improve speed by two orders of magnitude,
and first results are close -- the speedup for the code
converted to C is 95 to 1.
The code converted to C remains wrappered in Perl.
The Perl wrapper handles the I/O,
the user interface, and roughly the last third of the core algorithm.
This last part of the core algorithm I have yet to rewrite in C.
&lt;p&gt;The speedup for an actual application depends
on how much Perl &quot;wrappering&quot; the application layers on top of the Marpa parse engine.
But every test in the test suite is several times faster
for XS than for Pure Perl.
Ultimately, I will make Marpa's core algorithm available
as &lt;var&gt;libmarpa&lt;/var&gt;, a C library with a documented interface.
If you write a wrapper for &lt;var&gt;libmarpa&lt;/var&gt; in C,
you will be able to get the full speedup, which I expect
with a few more tweaks to be better than 100 to 1.
&lt;h1&gt;Looking Onward: An &quot;Official&quot; Alpha Release&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this moment,
Marpa::XS is available in developer's releases only.
I prefer that most users look at
&lt;a href=&quot;http://search.cpan.org/dist/Marpa/&quot;&gt;Marpa&lt;/a&gt; instead.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://search.cpan.org/dist/Marpa/&quot;&gt;Marpa&lt;/a&gt; is Pure Perl.
It is also alpha,
but it is stable at this point.
&lt;p&gt;But with this very measurable speedup,
Marpa::XS now offers added value over
&lt;a href=&quot;http://search.cpan.org/dist/Marpa/&quot;&gt;Marpa&lt;/a&gt;,
and I am turning to work on
an &quot;official alpha&quot; release of Marpa::XS.
Such a release would still not be suitable for use in production
situations, and its interface would be subject to change.
&lt;h1&gt;Notes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;NOTE1&quot;&gt;Note 1&lt;/a&gt;:
Technically, the grammars that Marpa parses in linear time are the
LR-regular grammars.
These include the LR(k) grammars and the LL(k) grammars, for all k.
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;NOTE2&quot;&gt;Note 2&lt;/a&gt;:
The claim of O(n) time complexity is for the underlying algorithm.
Actual implementations tend to pick those data structures
which are fastest in practice, instead of on paper.
Pure Perl implementations, of course,
must rely on the internal implementation
of Perl's native data structures.
&lt;p&gt;The relationship between theoretical time complexity
and actual implemented speed in our field is like that
between quantum mechanics and Newtonian mechanics in physics.
There are effects back and forth, and a realm
where each clearly rules.
There are also specialists in each,
who tend to avoid looking at the scales
where one set of rules ceases to apply
and the other kicks in.
&lt;p&gt;The relationship between
theoretical time complexity and actual implemented speed interests
me.
In Marpa's XS implementation, I have control of the data
structures, and I am using the implementation to work out
in detail
the proofs of time complexity for Earley's algorithm
and Leo's modification of it.
In the course of this I hope to make a full accounting of
any differences
between theoretical and implemented time complexity.</description>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
